Sam Smith Collection
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
Sam Smith Collection
1972-1996
1972-1979
MSS.14
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
4
The collection comprises original work by Sam Smith including ink drawings, mock-ups, hand-carved wooden boats, paper model sets, typescripts, and correspondence.
Smith, Sam, 1908-
Biographical / Historical
British artist Sam Smith is best known for his hand-carved wooden toys and sculpture. He was born on 27 July, 1908, in Southampton, England. His father, Edwin Thomas Smith, was a steamship captain and a great influence on Smith's art. Smith often depicts themes of the sea, including boats, sea side towns, mermaids, and sea captains.
Smith was educated at Victoria College, Jersey, between 1918 and 1925, and later at Bournemouth School of Art and Westminster School of Art, London, from 1926 to 1930. He aspired to become a painter, but even after one of his paintings was exhibited at the Royal Academy of Arts in 1925, he did not find success. In 1933 he became an assistant at the Little Gallery in London. While at the Little Gallery, Smith began carving small wooden objects; these later transformed into wooden toys sold at the gallery. By 1935, he began to receive some critical recognition.
Smith's activity creating wooden sculpture was interrupted by World War II, during which he was sent to work as an illustrator of bridge-building manuals for GTC Redbridge Bailey Bridge Company. Smith's experience rendering technical drawings would later prove helpful in his own career as an artist and sculptor.
After 1945, and with the help of Henry Rothschild, Smith began to exhibit his work more frequently, with shows at Primavera, London, and later at the Portal and Serpentine Galleries in London. Smith's work continued to increase in popularity and he began producing on a larger scale. He soon began to supply toys to department stores, boutiques, and private collectors.
Smith's work was widely received in the United States after 1955. He achieved far greater success in the American market, where he developed a cult-like following. The more successful he became, the more expansive and ambitious were his pieces, including some large-scale wooden sculpture, paper cut-out books, and toy theaters. Smith had many dedicated patrons and promoters, including Max and Barbara Wilk, and in 1972 the Bristol City Art Gallery held his first major retrospective exhibition. The exhibition later traveled to Camden Arts Centre, London, and the Beauford Arts Centre, Devon. This exhibition was extremely successful and gave Smith the recognition in his home country that he had previously enjoyed in the United States.
Other exhibitions would follow and some are written about in his letters to Max and Barbara Wilk. In 1976, BBC2 Arena released an award-winning film, Sam Smith: Genuine England. In the early 1980s Smith had a major exhibition at The Serpentine Gallery, London. Illness followed soon thereafter, and Smith died in 1983.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Max and Barbara Wilk.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into eight series: I. Bioscope Palace; II. Edward and His Marvellous Telescope; III. Trudi, Angela and John Darme; IV. Paper Model Sets; V. Carved and Painted Wood Sculpture; VI. Exhibition Material; VII. Correspondence; and VIII. Miscellaneous
Scope and Contents
The collection comprises original work by Sam Smith including ink drawings, mock-ups, hand-carved wooden boats, paper model sets, and typescripts for three unpublished works: Bioscope Palace, Edward and his marvellous telescope, and Trudi, Angela and John Darme. One of these unpublished works, Bioscope Palace, illustrates Smith's interest in toy theater and silent cinema.
Also present is related correspondence, primarily between Smith and Max and Barbara Wilk. The letters cover many topics, including Smith's unpublished works and his exhibitions. Letters in the collection are from the period of ambition and recognition that Smith enjoyed in the 1970s. The tone is personal and comical and it is obvious that Smith took great care in producing the letters, as they are always hand addressed and signed with love from Sam. The collection also includes secondary material about Smith, including exhibition catalogs and magazine clippings
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Bibliography
Lister, Eric. Twentieth Century British Naïve and Primitive Artists. London: Astragal Books, 1977.
Burr, James. "An Alternative Art." Apollo, Dec. 1980, p. 428.
Sam Smith: Genuine England. 2003. Jessica Jewett and Jamie Ridyard. 8 Dec. 2011 http://www.sam-smith.org/
Pasierbska, Halina. "Smith, Alan Verner [Sam] (1908-1983)" Oxford dictionary of National Biography. 2004. Oxford University Press. 8 Dec. 2011 http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/93092>
Sam Smith: Genuine England, Arena, BBC2, 1976.
Artists -- Great Britain; Handicraft -- Great Britain; Paper toys -- Great Britain; Sculpture -- Great Britain; Toymakers -- Great Britain; Toys -- Great Britain; Brochures; Clippings; Cut-out craft; Exhibition catalogs; Gouaches; Graphite drawings; Pen and ink drawings; Legal documents; Letters; Magazines (periodicals); Miniature theaters; Mock-ups; Models (representations); Photocopies; Postcards; Recreations; Toy theaters; Typescripts; Watercolors; Wood engravings; Begaye, Mary Frances; Benn, Timothy, 1936-; Lister, Eric; Sachs, Judith; Smith, Sam, 1908-; Westermann, H. C. (Horace Clifford), 1922-1981; Wilk, Barbara; Wilk, Max, 1920-; Arts Council of Great Britain; British Broadcasting Corporation; Camden Arts Centre; Crafts Advisory Committee; Ernest Benn Ltd; Farrar, Straus, and Giroux; Portal Gallery (London, England); Serpentine Gallery
- Bioscope Palace, Series I
  - Correspondence
    - Letter to Max, Barbara and Francie Wilk, 1974; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 3 leaves; 26 x 21 cm. Typescript letter addressed and signed in black ink. Heading dated: "the ninth 1974" (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      The letter refers to the "Silent Cinema Toy," later known as the Bioscope Palace. There is also a reference to an unidentified publication with "thirty 2" pages of illustrations for Ernest Benn Ltd.
      Correspondence; Ernest Benn Ltd; Wilk, Max, 1920- -- Correspondence; Begaye, Mary Frances -- Correspondence; Wilk, Barbara -- Correspondence; Smith, Sam, 1908- -- Correspondence
    - Letter to Max Wilk, 1974 August 4; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf; 26 x 21 cm. Typescript letter addressed and signed in pen, with purple ink stamp of Sam Smith below signature. (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Letter mentions the "Silent Cinema Toy," later referred to as the Bioscope Palace: "Have come to the conclusion some form of pictures turning on rollers is the right answer, and Jasper is now supposed to be making a mock-up model." The header of the letter is addressed: The Golf House Kingswear Dartmouth Devon England Europe The World Solar System Universe Lap of God.
      Correspondence; Wilk, Max, 1920- -- Correspondence; Smith, Sam, 1908- -- Correspondence
    - Letter to Max and Barbara Wilk, 1975 September 17; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 5 leaves; 26 x 21 cm. Typescript letter addressed and signed in ink. Letter includes sketches of the "Silent Cinema" later known as the Bioscope Palace. Some sketches hand-colored. Leaf 1-2 on white paper. Leaves 3-4 are on pink paper. Leaf 5 on Sam Smith letterhead with portrait of The Founder. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Letter discusses an upcoming visit by a photographer, F. Bullock, for the purpose of gathering material for a book on crafts. It includes sketches for the "Silent Cinema" later known as the Bioscope Palace.
      Correspondence; Smith, Sam, 1908- -- Correspondence; Wilk, Barbara -- Correspondence; Wilk, Max, 1920- -- Correspondence
    - Letter to Max Wilk, 1978 September 6; Sachs, Judith; 1 leaf; 27 x 19 cm. Typescript letter on Hawthorn Books letterhead. Signed in black pen by Judith Sachs. Includes original envelope with Hawthorn books, Inc. label on verso. (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Sachs discusses how everyone loves Sam's work but that no one can figure out how to make the theater idea work.
      Hawthorn Books, Inc. merged with EP Dutton in 1979.
      Correspondence; Wilk, Max, 1920- -- Correspondence; Smith, Sam, 1908-; Sachs, Judith -- Correspondence
  - Artwork
    - Sketched mock-up design of Bioscope Theatre, 1970s; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 mock-up; 25 x 30 cm. folded to 25 x 16 cm. Constructed from manila folder and sketched on with red pen. Includes 1 strip of scenes, 7 x 22 cm. (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Mock-up shows both the printed and mechanical design of the theater. The folder was previously used to keep files regarding Judith Sachs; it is labeled in pen, "Judith Sachs 6/12/78."
      Toy theaters; Miniature theaters; Mock-ups; Sachs, Judith
    - Advertisement design for Bioscope Palace, 1970s; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf; 28 x 21 cm. Colored felt marker and graphite on white paper. 4 x 6 cm piece of paper glued to sheet. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Preliminary colored drawing of a design for a Bioscope Palace advertisement. It states that the Bioscope Palace is the "home of FINE ENTERTAINMENT for ALL the FAMILY."
      Pen and ink drawings; Mock-ups; Toy theaters; Miniature theaters
    - Advertisement design for Bioscope Palace, 1970s; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf; 25 x 22 cm. Colored felt marker and graphite on white paper. (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Drawn in color, advertisement design for Bioscope Theater. "Coming! Don't Miss It! Limited Engagement Hurry!"
      Pen and ink drawings; Mock-ups; Miniature theaters; Toy theaters
    - Program cover design for Bioscope Palace, 1970s; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf; 28 x 22 cm. Colored felt tip marker and graphite on white paper. (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Program design for the Bioscope Palace drawn in colored felt tip marker. Some preliminary graphite lines remain.
      Mock-ups; Pen and ink drawings; Miniature theaters; Toy theaters
    - Prototype of Bioscope Palace, 1974; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 miniature theater, 2 strips of scenes, 1 strip of announcements; theater 23 x 46 cm + 2 strips of scenes 13 x 55 cm, 1 strip of announcements 13 x 26 cm. (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Mechanical prototype design of a miniature or toy theater with three strips. Designed as a replica of a 1910-style motion picture theater illustrated with pen and ink and watercolor. The two strips of scenes include 12 captioned drawings of scenes imitating early film. The other strip has illustrated announcements to the audience. All are hand-colored with pen and black ink, watercolor and colored felt-tip pen.
      Miniature theaters; Toy theaters; Mock-ups
  - Miscellaneous
    - Letter of agreement regarding "Biograph Palace", 1974 June 19; Smith, Sam, 1908-; Wilk, Max, 1920-; 1 leaf; 28 x 22 cm. Typescript contract signed in ink. (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Typescript contract stating the basis for an agreement between Sam Smith and Max Wilk, regarding the possible publication of the "Biograph Palace" prototype as a mass-produced toy, book, or both.
      Legal documents; Smith, Sam, 1908-; Wilk, Max, 1920-
    - Typescript. Description of Bioscope palace, 1970s; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 2 leaves; 28 x 22 cm. Typescript. (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Narrative typescript description of the Bioscope Palace as "the finest of that most exciting new invention, the moving picture play."
      Typescripts
- Edward and His Marvellous Telescope, Series II
  - Correspondence
    - Postcard to Barbara Wilk, 1972 September 7; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 postcard; 9 x 14 cm. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Addressed to Mrs. Barbara Wilk, 14 Eton Villas, London, N.W.3. "Thursday Have brought my telescope to Wolver-Hampton for a new view. Wish you were here, Sam."
      Postcard with four pictures of Wolverhampton, including Town Hall, West Park, St. Peter's Collegiate Church, and Victoria Street.
      Postcards; Wilk, Barbara -- Correspondence; Smith, Sam, 1908- -- Correspondence
    - Letter to Max and Barbara Wilk, 1973 March 14; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf; 30 x 21 cm. Typescript letter on light orange paper. Addressed and signed in blue ink. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      The third paragraph of the letter discusses the "telescope idea" and Sam's wish to work out some rough sketches to send along with his next correspondence. Sam also mentions that he has enclosed a recently completed "do-it-yourself cutout."
      Correspondence; Wilk, Barbara -- Correspondence; Wilk, Max, 1920- -- Correspondence; Smith, Sam, 1908- -- Correspondence
    - Letter to Max Wilk, 1974 August 2; Benn, Timothy, 1936-; 1 leaf; 30 x 21 cm. Typescript letter to Max Wilk from Timothy Benn on Ernest Benn Ltd. letterhead. Addressed and signed in blue ink. (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Letter discusses putting the manuscript of Edward and His Marvellous Telescope in the post that afternoon and sending it to another publisher, Farrar Straus. Mr. Benn explains that they are currently working on The Secret Harbour (another work by Sam Smith) and how he would like to complete that project before embarking on another. He is, however, very interested in the concept of Edward and hopes to make it a companion book to the The Secret Harbor after "a good deal of modification."
      Correspondence; Farrar, Straus, and Giroux; Smith, Sam, 1908-; Ernest Benn Ltd; Wilk, Max, 1920- -- Correspondence; Benn, Timothy, 1936- -- Correspondence
    - Letter to an unidentified recipient, 1970s; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf; 21 x 15 cm. Autograph signed letter in blue ink on The Victoria Hotel letterhead. (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Letter thanks the recipient for his previous letter and discusses thinking about telescopes in the Prince Albert Room and going to Birmingham to think some more.
      Correspondence; Smith, Sam, 1908- -- Correspondence
    - Letter to Max Wilk, before 1979; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf; 30 x 21 cm. Typescript letter to Max Wilk on light orange paper. Addressed and signed in black ink. (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Most of the letter discusses health issues (of Sam and Barbara Wilk), a farm, and farm animals. The final paragraph reads: "My gosh it will be good if Ed and his Telescope take off. I hope we can keep plenty of words. Surely up to ten thousand would be all right (12,000). Love to all, Sam"
    - Letter to Barbara Wilk, before 1979; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf; 30 x 21 cm. Typescript letter on light orange paper. Addressed and signed in blue ink. (Box 1, Folder 16)
      The first two paragraphs of the letter discuss health issues. The next two paragraphs discuss the "Telescope project," including a first chapter for a "Telescope theme." Smith adds that there is a drawing of "the place", "drawings of the Captain-loving and Dis-approving--could be a two-faced cut-out," and "a trick drawing--the opening of the water machine as seen through Edward's telescope."
      Correspondence; Wilk, Barbara -- Correspondence; Smith, Sam, 1908- -- Correspondence
  - Artwork
    - Signed drawings of the Captain, 1970s; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 sheet; 33 x 26 cm. 2 sheets of white watercolor paper adhered together. Drawn with colored pen and signed on both sides. (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Each side of the sheet has an emotional depiction of the Captain. One side declares: "The Captain...could be a loving man." The other side counters: "He could also be a strongly disapproving man."
      Pen and ink drawings
    - Signed drawing of a scene through the telescope, 1970s; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 sheet; 33 x 26 cm. 1 sheet of white paper and one sheet of black adhered together. Black sheet has circular cutout opening to a colored illustration on the white paper. The illustration has a flap that can be lifted to show another colored illustration. (Box 4, Folder 3)
      The illustration depicts a scene from Edward and His Marvellous Telescope, as if the viewer were looking through a telescope. Under the illustration Smith has written "through the telescope." Above the picture Smith notes: "Lift to see what happened next." When a flap is lifted there is another scene from the story on the other side.
    - Signed drawing of Harmouth harbor, 1970s; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 sheet; 33 x 51 cm. Pen and black ink drawing with colored felt-tip pen, watercolor and gouache. Was once folded in half and creased in the middle. (Box 4, Folder 4)
      Drawing is of Harmouth harbor and depicts Edward's lonely white cottage on one side of the harbor and the populated port on the other. Below the drawing, in black felt-tip pen is written: "Any stranger coming for the first time to the small port of Harmouth who might wonder who lived in the small white cottage which stood alone on the far side of the harbour had only to ask and they would be told, 'Edward lives there with his grandfather.' All the town knew Edward and his grandfather, though only in a distant sort of way; for people could not quite understand why anyone should choose to live in such a lonely place when they could be cosily crowded together with everyone else in the town." Signed on the bottom right in black ink.
      Pen and ink drawings; Gouaches; Watercolors
  - Miscellaneous
    - Typescript of Chapter 1 and a one-page development of rest of story, 1970s; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 15 leaves; 26 x 21 cm. Typescript with corrections. 14 leaves on white paper, 1 leaf on green paper. Includes original folder with title drawn in ink and 9 x 15 cm. note signed by Timothy Benn in blue ink. (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Typescript leaves contain chapter 1 of Edward and his Marvellous Telescope and includes a one-leaf synopsis of "How the story would continue: "The story takes place in the small port of Harmouth. The characters are Edward, his grandfather (the Captain), Primrose (the Harbour Authority's steamer that Edward's grandfather was once the captain of), Major Swivel, Edward's telescope, The Mayor Ma'am, The Harbour Authority, and others."
- Trudi, Angela and John Darme, Series III
  - Correspondence
    - Letter to Barbara Wilk, 1972 November 8; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf; 26 x 21 cm. Typescript letter addressed and signed in purple ink. Additional notation in ink on right side edge of letter. (Box 1, Folder 18)
      The typescript portion of the letter states that Sam has completed the story of Trudi and Angela, but has not completed the drawings due to a hospitalization. There is also a brief note about completing the full draft of "the telescope story." Along the edge of the letter on the right-hand side Sam writes, in ink, "Elections sadden me because humans are always so much more credulous than I hope."
    - Letter to Barbara Wilk, 1973 January 23; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf; 26 x 21 cm. Typescript letter on pink paper signed in ink. (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Letter mainly talks about Smith's personal health and that of "Glad's." There is a brief entry stating, "It will be marvellous if anything comes of the Trudi-Angela piece."
    - Letter to Barbara Wilk, before 1979; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf; 26 x 21 cm. Typescript letter addressed and signed in ink. (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Smith's letter discusses the contents of an enclosure (not included), which consisted of photocopies of letters that he wrote to a young girl in the hospital. He describes the letters as something that he once did and still does "naturally."
      Correspondence; Smith, Sam, 1908- -- Correspondence; Wilk, Barbara -- Correspondence
  - Artwork
    - Shall we go to the beach?, 1970s; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf; 26 x 21 cm. Pen and black ink and colored felt-tip pen on white paper. (Box 4, Folder 5)
      Depicts a sheep and a dog facing one another in conversation below a sun. Gray gouache frame is painted around image.
      Pen and ink drawings; Gouaches
    - The end of the day on the beach, 1970s; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf; 28 x 22 cm. Pen and black ink and colored felt-tip pen on white paper. (Box 4, Folder 6)
      Depicts a man in uniform (John Darme?), a sheep, and three dogs, dancing around a broom stick with flags. At bottom is a note in black ink: "short authorised version" and "see p. 127." The drawing is 1 of 3 samples enclosed with a signed typescript of Trudi, Angela and John Darme with illustrations and colored title page.
      Watercolors; Pen and ink drawings
    - Going home, 1970s; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf; 29 x 22 cm. Pen and black ink and colored felt-tip pen on white paper. (Box 4, Folder 7)
      The drawing depicts a man in uniform riding a bicycle with a ladder, a sheep, and three dogs. It is stamped in purple ink "Sam Smith, England." The drawing is 1 of 3 samples enclosed with a signed typescript of Trudi, Angela and John Darme with illustrations and colored title page.
    - Lottie and Liza lazing on a flower bed., 1970s; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf; 26 x 21 cm Pen and black ink and colored felt-tip pen on white paper. (Box 4, Folder 8)
      Depicts two dogs lying in a flowerbed eating chocolate biscuits.
      Pen and ink drawings; Watercolors
    - Trudi pretends to be a witch and makes Angela laugh until her wool goes straight, 1970s; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf; 26 x 21 cm. Pen and black ink and colored felt-tip pen on white paper. (Box 4, Folder 9)
      Depicts a dog in a witch costume, and a sheep laughing. "See page 147" is written below the tile.
    - Trudi's house: drawn by hand from a photograph, 1970s; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf; 26 x 21 cm. Pen and black ink and colored felt-tip pen on white paper. (Box 4, Folder 10)
      Depicts a house with two doors and a walkway in the foreground. The doors are colored blue and pink and there is a yellow ring around the house.
      Pen and ink drawings; Graphite drawings
    - Untitled drawing for Trudi, Angela and John Darme, 1970s; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf; 26 x 21 cm. Pen and black ink drawing on white paper. (Box 4, Folder 11)
      The drawing depicts a house with two doors and two trees in the foreground. At bottom-left is a note in black ink: "short authorised version." The drawing is 1 of 3 samples enclosed with a signed typescript of Trudi, Angela and John Darme with illustrations and colored title page.
  - Miscellaneous
    - Signed typescript of Trudi Angela and John Darme with illustrations, 1970s; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 18 leaves; 26 x 21 cm. Typescript, with corrections and annotations in pen and black ink. (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Most leaves are typescript. A note on the title page reads: "Draft of the expanded version; the illustrations--lots of them--would be in the style of the four samples [i.e. the four illustrations listed above]." The typescript includes one colored illustration and two additional black ink illustrations embedded in the text.
    - Signed typescript of Trudi Angela and John Darme with illustrations and colored title page, 1970s; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 12 leaves; 26 x 21 cm. (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Typescript title page has ink colored title with illustration of the sun. Below this Smith has typed: "A hot-up of the short Authorised Version. Illustrations, as 3 samples, would be simple in colour and look as if they had been drawn by anybody's uncle. Love to all Sam." Includes two illustrations in pen and black ink embedded in the text. The three samples that Smith refers to are "Untitled," "Going Home," and "The end of the day on the beach," listed above.
    - Photocopy of manuscript and typescript of Trudi and Angela, incomplete, 1970s; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 18 leaves; 33 x 21 cm. (Box 1, Folder 23)
      The photocopied pages of Trudi and Angela, as explained in the letter to Barbara Wilk, are "all that remains of letters I wrote to a small child in hospital some years ago..." Some letters are hand written, others are typescript. There are illustrations.
      It pages were an enclosure with the Barbara Wilk letter included in the present series.
      Photocopies
- Paper Model Sets, Series IV